Mark McDermott

Downers Grove, Illinois 60515 Cell: 312-925-2991

heymcdermott@gmail.com www.markmcdermott.com

SUMMARY

Technologically savvy, using the latest and best advances to provide quality, cost-effective end product. A quick study, intuitive in learning new applications and processes, and who continually explores new capabilities and procedural efficiencies. An accomplished professional in Writing, Graphic Production, Desktop Composition, Prepress and Publishing. Now leveraging computer publishing experience into online platforms.

TECHNOLOGY/SOFTWARE

- Adobe Creative Suite CC 2014: InDesign, Illustrator, Photoshop, Dreamweaver
- Microsoft Office 2011: Word, Excel, PowerPoint
- Kindle, Nook, iBook publishing
- Acrobat Pro with EnFocus PitStop OpenOffice, WordPerfect (Pre-press software)
- Quark XPress, FrameMaker
- FileMaker Pro
- WordPress, Blogger, Drupal blogging; SEO support.
- Windows 8 or Mac OS X 10.8
- Basic Web Design: HTML5, CSS, JQuery, Oracle, XML, PHP, SQL, Ruby
- Red Rock **DeltaGraph**

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

Allstate Insurance, Northbrook, Illinois (Contractor through Creative Circle, Chicago) March 2014–April 2015

Rebranding Specialist: Converted insurance policies and related documents from in Word: applied current branding; and set PDFs and data merge text for new content management system. Created macros to format documents twice as fast as predecessor. Over 2,400 documents converted in 12 months.

Freelance Book Publisher

March-Sep. 2014

Laid out and formatted 300-page book, The Book of Iowa Films by Marty Knepper & John S. Lawrence, to accompany "Hollywood in the Heartland" exhibit at State Historical Museum of Iowa. Set InDesign to Lulu print-on-demand, then eBook formats for Amazon Kindle, Barnes & Noble Nook and Apple iBooks.

Schawk!, Chicago, Illinois

Sep.-Nov. 2013

Seasonal Desktop Specialist: Produced Sears and Kmart newspaper ads for "Black Friday" holiday season. Used InDesign CS 6.0 with Comosoft LAGO4 for managing copy, price data, and graphic assets. Retouched photos, pre-flighted pages for printing. Helped speed production and reduce errors during contract renegotiation period.

Freelance and Contract Work, Booked through Creative Circle, City Staffing (Chicago), and Digital People (Rolling Meadows, Illinois)

May 2011-Feb. 2014

- Highlights of several short-term assignments for agencies, corporations and non-profit organizations:
- National Opinion Research Center, Chicago, Produced proposals, organizational charts, flyers and publications, using Adobe Creative Suite 6.0, Word and PowerPoint.
- Reach Creative, Chicago. Edited responses to Requests for Proposals for agency client Williams Interactive's bids to the Delaware Lottery.
- LabelMaster, Chicago. Produced Word templates for manufacturer of regulatory compliance labels to industry and transportation. Templates allow customers to print their own information on labels.
- William Blair & Co., Chicago, Re-branded 150 internal Word & InDesign forms for global investment and financial services firm.
- Rivet/DraftFCB Agency, Chicago. Laid out white papers, designed Word and Power Point templates for client Microsoft Public Sector Sales.
- Patterson Medical, Bolingbrook, Illinois. Composed over 300 catalog pages in Quark XPress.
- American Institutes for Research, Naperville, Illinois. Formatted Word and PowerPoint templates.

Pearson Education, Lombard, Illinois

March-May 2012 & 2013

Test Scorer: Scored 8,500 essay pages for math & reading in Illinois Standards Achievement Tests (ISATs).

R.R. Donnelley & Sons Co., Downers Grove, Illinois

Premedia Technician, Automated Publishing division.

Jan. 2005 - Apr. 2011

- Laid out books and directories, and ran prepress inspections on Acrobat PDF files to ensure they would print properly under strict standards required by client or Donnelley sites.
- **Documents included** association membership directories, HMO/PPO benefit packages with physician directories, hotel chain directories, wholesale and retail parts catalogs.

- **Served clients including** UnitedHealthcare, Blue Cross/Blue Shield agencies, Coventry Healthcare, Gates Automotive, Archdiocese of Chicago, American Honda Motorcycle, Motor Coach International, Maryland DOT, S.P. Richards, International Society of Arboriculture.
- Turned around work that had been outsourced faster than overseas sites, cutting errors and revisions.
- Created or scanned client graphics, made color changes for print or internet publication.
- Converted high resolution printing photos and complex Illustrator vector graphics into internet-ready JPEGs for client web sites and online PDFs.
- Dramatically shortened turnaround for catalog pages produced from desktop, saving office production time, and contributing to 10% annual reduction in department production cost.
- Produced large health insurance documents in 135 separate editions. Reduced production errors and inconsistencies by 90%, shortened turnaround time, greater client satisfaction.
- Conformed insurance carrier documents to Department of Health & Human Services' Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) Section 508(c) standards for accessible PDFs.

R.R. Donnelley & Sons Co., Chicago, Illinois

Desktop Publishing Technician, Financial Printing division.

July 1996 – Dec. 2004

- **Produced financial documents** and supporting graphics for printed stakeholder materials in Capital Markets and Investor Services, and for filing with the U.S. Securities & Exchange Commission (SEC).
- **Worked on documents** related to corporate governance including Initial Public Offerings, Annual and Semiannual Reports, quarterly performance reports, and prospectuses for managed funds.
- **Served clients including** Nuveen Investments, Invesco/Van Kampen, Security Capital, Thrivent Financial for Lutherans, Wanger Investment Management, William Blair & Co., BankOne (Chase).
- Standardized financial graphs with numerical data appended for composition system with output in print and HTML, and text markup version for reading on the SEC's text-only EDGAR website.
- Implemented tracking of Desktop department's activities in FileMaker Pro database to identify more accurate billing information in meeting Department's budget. Increased billing charges by 40%.
- Worked with transition to current industry workflow of PDF to printing plate.

Tribune Community Publications, Chicago, Illinois

1989 – 2004

Freelance Writer. Produced articles in support of various **Chicago Tribune** sections.

- Wrote "advertorial" supporting advertisers in special sections: Silver Years, Brides & Grooms, Lawn & Garden, How-To Guides, and the Michigan Avenue Magnificent Mile Lights Festival.
- Interviewed people in various jobs for Sunday CareerBuilder classified section.

Pennysaver Publications, Tinley Park, Illinois

1987 – 1989

Editor/Writer. Wrote articles for local free shopper.

- Edited and wrote feature stories for local community guides and summer festival programs.
- Wrote features and edited Business-to-business magazine, Chicagoland Quarterly Business Review.

OTHER EXPERIENCE

Writer and video blogger (iMovie) on Chicago's craft beer scene for **Beeronaut.com** (WordPress). Wrote guide article on Chicago taprooms for **Groupon.com**.

Radio announcer, news writer, disc jockey, music director at commercial and NPR stations.

EDUCATION

Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago. Master Certificate, Web Design & Application Development, 2013. **Bowling Green State University**, Bowling Green, Ohio. Master of Arts; Popular Culture. **Iowa State University**, Ames, Iowa. Bachelor of Arts; Speech/Journalism.

OTHER

Languages: Speak some German, typeset pages in Spanish, French, edited in Chinese, Japanese and Korean. **Academic Writer** on Popular Culture topics: Craft Beer Fan Culture, Spider-Man music LPs, *Star Wars*, Captain America, *Marvel Zombies*, James Bond movie songs, and *Mystery Science Theatre 3000*.

INTERNET PORTFOLIOS

linkedin.com/in/markrmcdermott

markmcdermott.contently.com

behance.net/MarkMcDermott